Alfred Freedman MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Alfred Freedman MD Papers
1936 - 2011
This collection contains the papers of Alfred M. Freedman, who was president of the American Psychiatric Association when the board of trustees changed the listing of “homosexuality” to “sexual orientation disturbance” in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders II (DSM-II). The collection has 10 series: Abuse of Psychiatry, Death Penalty, Ethics, Treatment of the Mentally Ill, Subject Files, Organizations, Writings, Correspondence, Photographs, and Memorabilia.
6.26 linear feet (15 boxes)
Freedman, Alfred M.
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
2011.0001
Gift of Paul Freedman, 2011.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Alfred Mordecai Freedman (1917 –2011) was born in Albany, New York and received his BA from Cornell University in 1937 and MD from the University of Minnesota in 1941. In 1943, he married Marcia Kohl, who was a labor economist at Columbia University. After his service as a medical officer in the US Army Corps during World War II, he worked with Dr. Harold Himwich on anti-cholinesterase agents. He received training as a resident in general and child psychiatry at Bellevue Hospital in 1948 and became the senior psychiatrist under Dr. Lauretta Bender of the children’s service. He served on the faculty of New York University from 1950 to 1955 and subsequently became the psychiatrist to the Department of Pediatrics of SUNY Downstate Medical Center in Brooklyn from 1955 to 1960, where he served on the Children’s Service at Kings County Hospital. At this time, he was the principal investigator on an NIH-supported project on the development of premature infants in the Bedford-Stuyvesant area of Brooklyn, which demonstrated the impact of poverty and deprivation and led to a program for stimulation and enrichment that was a precursor to Head Start.
In 1960, he became the first full-time Chairman and Professor of Psychiatry and the Behavioral Sciences at the New York Medical College (NYMC). The clinical base for the NYMC department was at the municipal Metropolitan Hospital in East Harlem, where a social and community psychiatry division was set up to work with community groups and agencies on maternal and child mental health, outreach programs in neighborhoods, community oriented programs for substance abuse, detoxification, cognitive rehabilitation of deprived children, and services directed to aiding the development of new housing for people with mental illness and residents of public housing, including the remodeling of buildings by the Upper Park Avenue Community Association (UPACA). This division at the Metropolitan Hospital received the first construction and staffing grant in New York State under the 1963 Comprehensive Community Mental Health Center Act.
After expanding the activities of the NYMC psychiatry program, Dr. Freedman realized the need for a comprehensive psychiatry textbook and became the Founding and Senior Editor of The Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, first published by Williams and Wilkins in 1967. When the medical school moved to Valhalla in Westchester County in 1980, Dr. Freedman continued to set up programs, including the Emergency Psychiatric Service for the county.
Dr. Freedman was President of the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology (1972-1973), the American Psychopathological Association (1971-1972), and Academia Medicinae and Psychiatriae (1990-1997). He also became the president of the American Psychiatric Association (APA) from 1973 to 1974 after being approached by the Committee of Concerned Psychiatrists to be the petition candidate in the 1972 election, which he won by a margin of three votes. During his presidency of the APA, the board of trustees changed the listing of “homosexuality” to “sexual orientation disturbance” in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders II (DSM-II). In addition, he led a group to the Soviet Union for the regional meeting of the World Psychiatric Association to discuss the question of psychiatric abuse and interview political dissidents in psychiatric hospitals while he was president of the APA. Although the interviews did not occur, the APA continued to focus on the misuse of psychiatry and psychiatrists in the Soviet Union. In addition, during Watergate, Nixon’s “Plumbers” broke into the office of Dr. Fielding, who was the psychoanalyst for Daniel Ellsberg, who had given the Pentagon Papers to the newspapers. Because of this breach of confidentiality, the APA with leading medical organizations organized a National Council on the Confidentiality of Medical Records, which Dr. Freedman was the first and only president of from 1973 to 1994.
Throughout his life, Dr. Freedman spoke out against the interrogation of people who are imprisoned or detained and the role of psychiatrists in executions. In addition, Dr. Freedman was the editor of the Political Psychology and Integrative Psychiatry journals and a Visiting Professor at Harvard Medical School. (1988-1993), the S.Y. Mak Visiting Professor at University of Hong Kong Medical School, and the Roche Visiting Professor in Australia and New Zealand through election by the Royal College. He received the first Wyeth-Ayerst Award for Distinction in Psychiatry for his contributions to the World Psychiatric Association’s objective to advance international cooperation in psychiatry in 1989. His other awards included the Samuel W. Hamilton Award of the American Psychopathological Association, the Jenne N. Knudson Award for Distinguished Service to the International Society of Political Psychology, the 2008 American Psychiatric Association Human Rights Award, and the Lapinlahti Medal and Lectureship, University of Helsinki. His research interests covered a range of topics, such as anti-cholinesterases, schizophrenia, biochemical basis of epilepsy, development of premature infants, drug addiction, opiate antagonists, and psychopharmacology in children and adults. He retired from the NYMC in 1989, but continued to be involved in professional organizations and activism related to psychiatry until his death in 2011.
Freedman, Alfred M.; American Academy of Psychiatry and the Law; Halpern, Abraham L.; American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology; American College of Neuropsychopharmacology; American College of Psychiatrists; American Psychiatric Association; American Psychopathological Association; Amnesty International; Capital punishment; Collegium Internationale Neuro-psychopharmacologicum; International Society of Political Psychology; New York Medical College; New York Medical College. Department of Psychiatry; Political psychology; Psychiatric ethics; Psychiatry--History; Psychiatry--Soviet Union; Psychiatry--United States; Psychopharmacology; World Association for Psychosocial Rehabilitation; World Psychiatric Association
This collection contains the papers of Alfred M. Freedman, who was president of the American Psychiatric Association when the board of trustees changed the listing of “homosexuality” to “sexual orientation disturbance” in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders II (DSM-II). There are 10 series in this collection.
Abuse of Psychiatry: This series contains files on the Daes Report and the abuse of psychiatry in the Soviet Union, China, and other countries.
Death Penalty: These materials document Dr. Freedman’s work and activities concerning the abolition of capital punishment and the involvement of psychiatrists in executions.
Ethics: These records cover a range of topics relating to psychiatry and ethics, including his work with the American Psychiatric Association and the Collegium Internationale Neuro-Psychopharmacologicum.
Treatment of the Mentally Ill: These folders contain information on this subject in general and Dr. Freedman’s activities concerning it.
Subject Files: These files document Dr. Freedman’s research and professional undertakings, including the metropolitan community mental health center and electroconvulsive therapy.
Organizations: This contains records on Dr. Freedman’s leadership in many professional organizations, including the American Psychiatric Association.
Writings: Original writings and printed materials from Dr. Freedman can be found in this series.
Correspondence: Dr. Freedman’s professional correspondence is in this series.
Photographs: This contains photographs from Dr. Freedman’s life and work, particularly at academic conferences.
Memorabilia: This series primarily has certificates documenting Dr. Freedman’s awards and leadership.
- Abuse of Psychiatry, This series contains files on the Daes Report and the abuse of psychiatry in the Soviet Union, China, and other countries.
  - Soviet Union
    - Analyses of the abuse of psychiatry in the Soviet Union, c. 1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence to Soviet officials about abuse of psychiatry, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Profiles of and related materials to Soviet abusers of psychiatry, 1973; 1975; undated (Box 1)
    - International League for the Rights of Man memos and related materials to Soviet abuses of psychiatry, 1972 - 1973; undated (Box 1)
    - Press releases and statements, 1971 - 1976; undated (Box 1)
    - News clippings on psychiatric abuse in the Soviet Union, 1973 - 1974; undated (Box 1)
    - Aspects of schizophrenia symposium in Soviet Union notes, printed materials, and correspondence, 1973 (Box 1)
    - "Schizophrenia in the Soviet Union" by Jimmie Holland, 1973; undated (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets on Soviet abuses of psychiatry, 1973; 1975 - 1976 (Box 1)
    - Notes by Dr. Freedman, 1973; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and articles regarding exchange between Soviet and American psychiatrists, 1987 - 1988 (Box 1)
    - American Psychiatric Association vote on exchange of information between psychiatrists of the United States and the Soviet Union, c. 1987 (Box 1)
    - Printed materials on "Breakthrough: Emerging New Thinking", 1987 (Box 1)
    - Senate hearing publication: "Abuse of Psychiatry for Political Repression in the Soviet Union", 1972 (Box 1)
    - "Report of the U.S. Delegation to Assess Recent Changes in Soviet Psychiatry", 1989; 2 folders (Box 1, Box 2)
    - Preliminary Soviet response to report of the U.S. Delegation, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Resolutions, agendas, and correspondence on the Soviet Union's readmittance to the World Psychiatric Association, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Articles on Soviet Union's readmittance into the World Psychiatric Association, 1983 - 1993 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence about articles on the Soviet Union's readmittance to the World Psychiatric Association, 1985 - 1986; 1989 (Box 2)
  - China
    - Correspondence Related to Psychiatric Abuse in China: Falun Gong, 2000 - 2004 (Box 2)
    - Printed materials on psychiatric abuse of Falun Gong practitioners, 1999 - 2001 (Box 2)
    - Bibliography- Abuse of Falun Gong Practitioners, undated (Box 2)
  - Other countries
    - Psychiatric abuse in North America book chapter, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Articles on the abuse of psychiatry in other countries, 2000 - 2001 (Box 2)
  - Daes Report
    - Correspondence and articles on the Daes Report, 1985 - 1991 (Box 2)
    - World Health Organization's principles for the treatment of the mentally ill and response to the Daes Report, 1988 (Box 2)
    - United Nations response to the Daes Report, 1989 - 1990; 1992 (Box 2)
- Death Penalty, These materials document Dr. Freedman’s work and activities concerning the abolition of capital punishment and the involvement of psychiatrists in executions.
  - American Medical Association and Council on Ethical and Judicial Affairs reports, action papers, and resolutions with correspondence, 1998 - 2002; 2006 - 2007 (Box 2)
  - Amnesty International, 1998 - 2001 (Box 2)
  - American Psychiatric Association action paper on the abolition of the death penalty, 1998; 2000 (Box 2)
  - Complaint against Dr. Fred Pintz for assisting with executions, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Complaints against doctors who assisted with the death penalty, 2001 - 2005 (Box 2)
  - Death penalty presentation notes and correspondence, 2001; 2006; undated (Box 2)
  - Death penalty correspondence, 1984 - 1985; 1996 - 1998; 2000 - 2002; 2006 (Box 2)
  - Insanity defense correspondence, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Letters in support of overturning the death penalty, 1998 - 1999; 2001 (Box 3)
  - New York Abolitionist correspondence, 2001 - 2002 (Box 3)
  - Other medical associations' action papers and resolutions on the abolition of the death penalty, 2000 - 2001 (Box 3)
  - Articles and letters to the editor by Dr. Freedman and Dr. Halpern, 1980; 1996; 1998 - 2002; 2006 (Box 3)
  - General articles on the death penalty, 1998 - 2002; 2005 - 2007 (Box 3)
  - Articles and correspondence on executions and mental illness, 1996; 1998 - 2002; 2006; undated (Box 3)
  - Articles on physicians and executions, 1996; 1998; 2000 - 2001; 2005 - 2008; undated (Box 3)
  - Annotated Psychiatric News article, "Sabshin Urges Cautious Use of Professional Authority", 1995 (Box 3)
  - Responses to Psychiatric Times letters to the editor, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Reports by the Death Penalty Information Center, 1996 - 1997 (Box 3)
  - Arthur Zitrin, 2005 - 2006; undated (Box 3)
  - Ethics and death penalty correspondence, articles, and publications, 1988; 1994 - 1998 (Box 3)
- Ethics, These records cover a range of topics relating to psychiatry and ethics, including his work with the American Psychiatric Association and the Collegium Internationale Neuro-Psychopharmacologicum.
  - Articles on the ethics of studies involving mentally ill patients, 1997; 1999 - 2001; 2003 - 2004 (Box 3)
  - Articles on financial ties to research, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Articles on side effects of anti-depressants, 2003 - 2004 (Box 3)
  - Articles on the use of placebos in studies, 2001 - 2003 (Box 3)
  - Guidelines on the ethics of relationships between psychiatrists and the pharmaceutical industry from the World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry and the Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Lowenkron v. Valente court case and research with patients unable to give consent, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and articles on David Healy and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), 2000 - 2004 (Box 4)
  - “A Statement of Principles of Ethical Conduct for Neuropsychopharmacologic Research in Human Subjects” from American College of Neuropsychopharmacology Council, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Articles on the ethics of forensic psychiatry, 1988; 2000; 2002 - 2003; 2006 - 2007 (Box 4)
  - Articles on torture, 2003; 2005; 2009 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and articles on the ethics of medicating mentally ill patients for competence, 2000; 2003 - 2007; undated (Box 4)
  - A modest proposal for the medical profession to introduce humane and civilized executions article draft and correspondence by Thomas Bewley, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Psychiatry and human rights correspondence, notes, and articles, 1973; 1998; 2000 - 2004; undated (Box 4)
  - Steven Miles articles and correspondence, 2006 - 2009; undated (Box 4)
  - Steven Miles professional codes and torture articles, notes, and correspondence, 2007 - 2009; undated (Box 4)
  - Synthetic sanity and forced psychotropic medication CINP presentations, notes, articles, and correspondence, 1993 - 1994; 2001 - 2004; undated (Box 4)
  - Ethics and neuropsychopharmacology CINP draft, articles, and correspondence, 1999; 2001; undated (Box 4)
  - Ethics and depression CINP articles and correspondence, 1997; 2001; 2003 - 2005 (Box 5)
  - Ethics and neuropsychopharmacology CINP draft and articles, 2003 - 2006; undated (Box 5)
  - American Psychiatric Association ethics controversy articles and reports, 1998; 2005 (Box 5)
  - American Psychiatric Association and ethics articles, publications, and correspondence, 1988 - 1989; 1991 - 1992; 1994 - 1996; 1998; 2001; 2003; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - General ethics articles and correspondence, 1990; 1999 - 2001; 2003 - 2005; 2008; undated (Box 5)
  - Confidentiality articles and correspondence, 1990; 1994; undated (Box 5)
  - Privacy and American business, 1993 - 1996; 2001 (Box 5)
- Treatment of the Mentally Ill, These folders contain information on this subject in general and Dr. Freedman’s activities concerning it.
  - Interrogation of detainees articles, correspondence, and reports, 2005 - 2006; 2008; undated (Box 5)
  - Insanity defense and Abraham Halpern articles, reports, and correspondence, 1980; 1983; 1988 - 1989; 1991 - 1994; 1997 - 1999; 2004; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - New York Times letter to the editor on adult homes from Alfred Freedman and Abraham Halpern, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Morton Birnbaum correspondence and legal briefs for Doe v. Shalala and Doe v. Thompson, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Deinstitutionalization and homelessness articles, reports, 1984; 1986 - 1998; 2001 - 2002; undated (Box 6)
  - Jeffrey Escoffier correspondence and chapters on mental health in nineteenth century New York, 1969 (Box 6)
- Subject Files, These files document Dr. Freedman’s research and professional undertakings, including the metropolitan community mental health center and electroconvulsive therapy.
  - Electroconvulsive therapy and Max Fink correspondence and articles, 1985; 2001 - 2005; undated (Box 6)
  - Electroconvulsive therapy book draft by Max Fink and Jan-Otto Ottosson, 2003 (Box 7)
  - Electroconvulsive therapy in Istanbul, Turkey correspondence, 2005 - 2006 (Box 7)
  - Post-traumatic stress disorder and children articles, 2004 (Box 7)
  - Mortality and mental illness articles, 2006 - 2008 (Box 7)
  - PsychRights' Medicaid fraud initiative against psychiatric drugging of children false claims act case, 2009 (Box 7)
  - Philosophy and history, 1988; 1990 - 1991; 1996; 2005; undated (Box 7)
  - Alzheimer’s and dementia articles and correspondence, 1996 - 1998; undated (Box 7)
  - Paradigm revisited articles, 1966 - 1968; 1974 - 1975; 1981; 1985; 1990; 1995; 1998 - 2004 (Box 7)
  - Future paper ideas articles and notes, 1977; 1985; 1992 - 1993; 1997; 2000 (Box 7)
  - American committee for the prevention and treatment of depression articles, correspondence, programs, and certificate, 1984 - 1995 (Box 7)
  - Multi-college medical university draft, 1969 (Box 7)
  - Mental health in the United States draft and articles, 1991; undated (Box 7)
  - Biographical material and endorsements, 1961; 1967 - 1968; 1972; 1974; 1977; 1982; 1989 - 1991; 2004; 2007 - 2009; 2011; undated (Box 8)
  - Metropolitan community mental health center correspondence, memos, and article drafts, 1970 - 1972; undated (Box 8)
  - Edward Acosta and the metropolitan community mental health center correspondence and memos, 1971; undated (Box 8)
  - Metropolitan hospital center conflict about leadership of community mental health center correspondence and poster, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Turan M. Itil partnership correspondence, memos, programs, notes, and proposals, 1981 - 1982; 1984 - 1985; 1988 - 1992; 1996 (Box 8)
  - Middle range plans by the New York Medical College drafts, 1970; undated (Box 8)
  - Brain hall of fame correspondence, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Names and addresses lists, 1989; undated (Box 8)
- Organizations, This contains records on Dr. Freedman’s leadership in many professional organizations, including the American Psychiatric Association.
  - Council of Global Psychiatry correspondence, notes, and minutes, 2002; 2006 - 2008 (Box 8)
  - American College of Neuropsychopharmacology correspondence, publications, articles, notes, and anniversary speech, 1991 - 1992; 1994 - 1998; 2000 - 2003; 2006; 2010; undated (Box 8)
  - American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology anniversary powerpoint and addresses, 2009 (Box 9)
  - Association for the Advancement of Philosophy and Psychiatry publications, presentations, and correspondence, 1994; 1997 - 2006 (Box 9)
  - World Psychiatric Association committee awards, 1989 (Box 9)
  - World Psychiatric Association section on education correspondence, minutes, and articles, 1990 - 2000 (Box 9)
  - International Society of Political Psychiatry correspondence, reports, and publications, 1991; 1993; 1997 - 2003 (Box 9)
  - American College of Psychiatrists publications and certificate, 1993; 2000; 2005 (Box 9)
  - Academia Medicinae, and Psychiatriae Foundation correspondence, directories, publications, and membership applications, 1985; 1988 - 1994; undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists tour, 1985; 1988; 1990 (Box 10)
  - International Foundation for Mental Health and Neurosciences correspondence, minutes, and articles, 1994; 1996; 1998 - 2003; undated (Box 10)
  - Collegium Internationale Neuro-Psychopharmacologicum publications and correspondence, 2001 - 2004 (Box 10)
  - International Foundation for Human Sciences and American Psychopathological Association presentations, articles, reports, and correspondence, 1988 - 1989; 1994 - 1995; 2001 - 2003; 2010 (Box 10)
  - American Academy of Psychiatry and the Law correspondence, publications, and articles, 1987; 1990 - 1991; 2000; 2002 - 2004 (Box 10)
  - Amnesty International correspondence, 1998 - 1999; undated (Box 10)
  - World Association for Psychosocial Rehabilitation publications, correspondence, articles, presentations, and brochure, 1991; 1993 - 1995; 1998 - 1999; 2001 - 2005; undated (Box 10)
  - International Center for Human Behavior and World Affairs correspondence, incorporation, and brochure, 1990; 1993 - 1995; 1998 - 1999; 2009; undated (Box 10)
  - World Psychiatric Association publications, photographs, and correspondence, 2002 - 2006 (Box 10)
  - American Psychiatric Association chronicles of a past president interview and article, 1996 (Box 10)
  - American Psychiatric Association presidential address: creating the future and key conference publications, 1974 (Box 10)
  - American Psychiatric Association profiles and awards programs, publications, and articles, 1977; 1988; 1990; 2005; 2007 - 2008 (Box 10)
  - American Psychiatric Association Board of Trustees correspondence, articles, reports, press releases, position statements, policy and procedures, presentations, and conference materials, 1991; 1996 - 2001; 2003 - 2009; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - American Psychiatric Association Washington D.C. board of trustees reports and agenda packet, 1973; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - American Psychiatric Association and deletion of homosexuality from DSM articles, powerpoint, notes, writings, oral history interview transcript, and correspondence, 1978; 1998 - 2001; 2006; 2008 - 2009; undated (Box 11)
  - American Psychiatric Association presidential memorabilia publications, correspondence, and programs, 1972 - 1974 (Box 11)
  - American Psychiatric Association Washington D.C. executive committee reports and agenda packet, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Conference programs, 1973 - 1974; 1979; 1981; 1984 - 1985; 1988; 1995 (Box 12)
- Writings, Original writings and printed materials from Dr. Freedman can be found in this series.
  - The Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry legal case correspondence, book agreements, meeting minutes, and notes, 1964; 1968 - 1974; 1976 - 1983; 1985; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - The Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry second and third editions correspondence, reviews, and publications, 1975 - 1982; 3 folders (Box 12, Box 13)
  - The Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry first and second editions correspondence, reviews, list of medical school textbooks, and meeting minutes, 1967 - 1969; 1971 - 1975 (Box 13)
  - Reprints and articles, 1955; 1962; 1966 - 1968; 1970 - 1973; 1975; 1977 - 1980; 1983 - 1986; 1988; 1990 - 1991; 1995 - 1996; 1998; 2003; undated (Box 13)